[Music]
thank you
hello everybody and welcome to the ask a
visit show it is that time of the week
again it's time for the ask of the show
and we are back after a gap of a week so
it's wonderful to be back once again
amongst you all
as always let us see who all is there on
the live stream I can see nikhil bimla
electron pumindui Tejas Rick Prince
namdeo
ayush Swami Mishra Sharma serious
student Pro Max
crypto gun whiteboard Ankita
um
foreign
side nickel Spaceman nikhil rushi abir
Banerjee Sanjay Kumar singing Siddhartha
pankaj spot Naman liger
harmonica hero Akash Narendra Bhai Modi
Naman panchal Amman
sanjoy Joel The Dreamer uh and lots of
other people subham parth mortis
rtkamlia Banerjee Raja Kumar SS Pala
application take my name sir yeah that's
your name
everybody else everybody else let me
stop here if you're already three
minutes into the show so uh greetings to
you all and thank you so much for being
on this live stream I hope you're doing
fantastically well so uh as as I'm sure
you all know this this episode is in
this episode I'm gonna take questions
from the live chat
uh I'm gonna bring back eventually the
episodes in which I take questions pre
pre-selected questions from the comments
that you all ask that you ask in the
comments but uh I believe that uh this
uh this format in which I take questions
live from the live chat is actually good
because you know it gives the
opportunity to more people to ask
questions and lots of people say that
you know I only take a few questions
from the from the uh comments so this is
more interactive it gives it gives more
people the opportunity to interact uh
with me and with everybody else so this
is fun actually you know so uh so let's
keep doing this for some time so uh yeah
let's let's get into the questions I'm
sure there's a lot to discuss there's
lots happening in the world uh so go for
it start asking your questions and let's
see how many I can take
they just says what's the mystery about
human-like statues on eastern island how
did people even go there in the first
place yeah where is Easter Island yeah
the time for the map time for the map
where is the map come on let's bring the
map in and take a look so where is
Easter Island we know where India is go
east east go east go east of Australia
go into the South Pacific Ocean Easter
Island is a tiny Island somewhere near
reasonably near Chile it's called Rapa
Nui let's let's search for it
r-a-p-a-n-u-i where is it
so it's part of Chile I think it belongs
to the nation state of Chile for
whatever reason
but here we are so this is okay so once
again let me zoom out just for reference
to understand where it is it's in the in
the vastness of the Pacific Ocean the
South Pacific Ocean enormous territory
of the Earth where there's almost
nothing except a few scattered islands
and there is this one Island there
called rapanui also called Easter Island
for whatever reason whatever reason it's
called East Ireland and it belongs to
the nation state of Chile so let's zoom
in now and let's see what is the size of
this island
as you can see it's a reasonably small
island let's measure the distance from
end to end from here to here it's about
23 kilometers
and from here to here not to South it's
about 12 13 kilometers so that's the
size of this island that's how large it
is it's it's it's quite small actually
and we have these moai these human
statues human-like statue is called moai
on this island I'm sure if we search for
it you will find it somewhere
there's an airport here
um
and I'm sure it's it's somewhere I'm not
gonna look okay something here right
let's let's take a look quickly if we
can see some of these things
all right okay so I'm not gonna maybe
it's these these little yeah here you
are there you are you see these these
shadows and these statues so these are
the human-like statues that you find on
this island okay I'm gonna zoom out and
let's talk let's talk about this uh
so let's let's see what these statues
look like let's go to Google search and
search for moai
uh Easter Island
Easter Island
this is this is what the statues look
like you know huge
large statues I'm sure many tons in
weight that's what it looks like and
they are more than half buried under the
Earth so it actually represents entire
human figures as you can see here this
gives you a better idea so that's what
it is about so what's the deal with
these human leg statues on Easter Island
this this island is essentially
uninhabited now so what happened is that
I don't know a long time ago it is the
Polynesian people who made their way to
this island they they migrated across
the vast the vast expanse of the almost
empty Pacific Ocean how they managed to
reach there it's it's a big mistake as
you as we just saw on the on the map
it's very isolated but they reached
there
there was a significant sizable
population of people there Polynesian
peoples the Easter Island people and
they had their own script I think it's
called The rongo rongo Script it is
suspiciously it is strangely uh
reminiscent of the Saraswati Hindu
script actually very strange it looks
similar in some ways and they had these
massive statues so because they are all
dead the entire population has been
wiped out I don't know when it happened
it happened at least a couple of
centuries ago uh
do some of them still survive maybe some
of them may survive on Chile or
something
in Chile I'm not sure I don't think any
of them still survives maybe some
descendants who are not pure blood May
survive perhaps but overall the people
died out because uh it's a small island
as we saw it can only sustain a certain
amount of people certain number of
people and eventually these people they
used up all the resources of the island
and there was nothing left no vegetation
no animals whatever and eventually you
know that caused the collapse of the
society and the population there and
eventually the the Europeans made their
way there and once Europeans reached
somewhere essentially you know nothing
nothing survives the Europeans are well
historically we know how they have been
they've wiped out entire continents
North America South America Australia so
what is Easter Island
uh
so these uh statues that we see the the
moai statues they represent their
culture their belief system maybe their
gods or their ancestors or great people
they wish to worship we're not quite
sure we're not quite clear there are
theories obviously you you'll look it up
online you will you will find multiple
theories of what these statues represent
but nobody has been able to reach any
consensus or any definitive conclusion
yet because the original culture no
longer exists it is only they who can
tell us what this really represented and
they are gone so it's still a mystery
maybe it will remain a mystery and you
know all this historical research is
typically done from a eurocentric
perspective
and when you do things if when you when
you study a non-european culture from a
eurocentric and way occidentalist
perspective you're gonna mess things up
so most historians have a very strong
eurocentric bias including Indian
historians and that's why this mystery
is is you know still a mystery and maybe
it will remain a mystery unless we're
able to decipher the script perhaps I'm
not sure the script has been deciphered
so that's what it's all about it's a
mystery we don't have the answers no
historian some historians claim to have
the answer but you know there has to be
a proper consensus
and consensus has to be based not on
opinions but on actual evidence and data
so a lot of evidence is missing the
people are no longer there and that is
why it is a mystery all right great
question to start with let us see
something else
let us see other questions
uh
Aditya Gupta says please express your
views on slowing economic growth the
so-called Hindu rate of growth so to say
compared to previous quarter what could
be could be done to reverse this listen
I'm not sure if the rate of growth today
is slowing down Hindu rate of growth I
mean that's the nehruvian rate of growth
that that for the the Lost Decades of
India's history after 1947 in which
India's economically two person three
person maybe four percent at Max per
year because of the socialistic policies
imposed by the great magnificent Mr
nehru
that was the nehruvian rate of growth
and it is certain Indian economists and
Western economists who coined the term
Hindu rate of growth to make fun of
Hindus and to you know demean India's
culture
so when a nation when India's economy
grows at two percent three percent of
per year three maybe four percent that's
what you would term as a nehruvian rate
of growth now how do you properly assess
the growth of a Nation you don't look at
it day by day or week by week or month
after month or quarter by quarter you
have to see it over an extended period
of time it at least one year at a time
right
so this year India's economy is
predicted to grow at what percent around
six percent per year that's what the IMF
or World Bank say that's okay that's
that projection that's a projection and
maybe you know already in in a year
there are four quarters maybe one
quarter the nation might not do may not
exp you know they can economy may not
grow very fast another quarter it may
grow at 13 per year something like that
happened last year right because of the
kickstarting of the economy after the
the lockdowns of the coronavirus
disaster
so we have to assess the growth of a
Nation over an extended period of time
minimum one year so let's wait until the
end of the year let's forget about the
projections projections are very useful
which which tells you this which gives
you a sense of how the economy is going
to fare it's good to have projections
but the assessment has to be done not
based on projections but on actual data
and we have to do it year after year and
of course the ones who are running the
country need to see day by day week by
week month by month quarter by quarter
but for us we should take a look at it
year after year one year at a time that
gives you a proper balanced objective
understanding of how the economy is
doing because you know there are
recalibrations and pivots that are done
on a week by week basis based on certain
things new Investments come in certain
things don't work well you have that's
you know like if you are if you're the
captain of a ship
so the actual performance of a captain
you don't see it minute by minute or or
you know hour after hour there may be
storms there may be squalls there may be
you know strong winds things happen so
you have to see it over a period of time
to actually assess the the performance
of a captain how well he or she is you
know uh captaining and leading so I I
would say that let's take a let's let's
uh not get ahead of ourselves uh we have
let's wait until the end of the year and
assess on December 31st or maybe
Financial whatever whichever way you
want to see it uh I think overall the
Indian economy is doing very well
India's economy I would say is poised
for a takeoff all the infrastructure we
have been building over the past eight
nine years all the reforms we've done we
have uh you know the GST it's old news
obviously but this is going to be the
foundation for the Indian economy taking
off the the uh the cashless the UPI
system that that's been brought in and
so many other things you know I think
India's economy is actually poised for a
takeoff the only bright spot in the
world
currently and for the sustainable for
the for the foreseeable future is going
to be India China is is Contracting
China's economy is really slowing down
even if they are projected to to grow at
5.6 percent of whatever for the next
year or whatever as per the IMF in World
Bank I don't really I I take these these
projections and statistics with a very
large serving of salt
because the Chinese are well known for
for putting out doctored manufactured
data
you cannot
ever trust their figures and their
statistics and their claims
okay the Chinese economy is actually
doing very poorly right now the last
couple of years it actually most likely
contracted despite whatever figures
they've put out
and it's going to only intensify because
of the impending demographic disaster
that they are there's no way for them to
escape that because of Decades of the
one child policy now the it's gonna come
home to roost you know all the all the
fruits of their Harvest
uh so even if they Implement a five
child policy now it's too late it's too
late by 2100 their population will be
half of what it is now and it will the
average age will be well into the 60s
the average person in China will be over
60 years old by 2050 by 2050 the average
Chinese person would be 58 or 57 years
old can you imagine that a nation of old
people
who's gonna
who's gonna sit in the tanks Who's Gonna
Fly the fighter planes who's gonna man
that enormous Navy they're building
who's gonna be in the submarines all
geriatric old people no they will find
young people to do that but you know it
significantly decreases the Vitality of
a Nation when everyone's old I have
nothing against old people but that's
simply how it is so the Chinese have
destroyed an entire straighta of their
population of their society you can see
it if you see any chart
of the Chinese population by by age
group you know zero to five five to ten
ten to Fifteen fifteen to twenty and so
on all the way up to 200 you will see
massive sections where you know there
are there are gaps
that you know the the the Chinese
population that grew up during the
so-called Great Leap Forward in the
cultural revolution Etc there are big
gaps there India's population curve is
very smooth the Chinese population curve
is like messed up so all these horrible
policies that they implemented they are
now showing their effects so China
is not going to do well the only economy
which can surpass the US in Maybe by 26
to 2070 it the latest is India there's
no other economy that can do that
not China for sure so overall long term
India's India's story this is going to
be in the Indian Century let's not look
at it quarter upon quarter that is a
very short-term way of looking at things
if you want to look at any person's
development already Nations development
or any City or States development you
have to have a reasonably long-term
perspective so I think it's going fine I
am not I I've not seen the the
whatever claims are being made
apparently looks like from from this
comment that economic growth will be
slowing but I don't I'm not concerned in
the least I think we are in we're in
good hands
okay
chirag says my friends say democracy was
found in Greece but being your viewer I
know it was found in India janapada how
can I explain the truth to them so okay
a good question uh democracy increase so
uh how how do we assess
you know what was the state of democracy
in India and in Greece so you know the
West
says that uh
if you look at the Western World the
Americans the the British Etc they say
that the West is a civilization western
civilization and uh its foundations are
Greece and Rome that's what they're
saying their foundations actually are
the Middle Ages the Dark Ages all that
but they want to disown that because
there was a horrible time and their
ancestors were responsible for that so
they try to claim that you know it is
Greece and Rome and maybe Mesopotamia
and Egypt that have contributed to uh
Western's religion and these are the the
Western Civilization is the birthplace
of democracy because Greece apparently
is the birthplace of democracy so
let's take a look at Greece let's
examine Greece your friends who say that
democracy was found in Greece why don't
you ask them a simple question when
somebody makes a claim you ask you you
have to ask ask a couple of questions
ask the question when did democracy
arise increase in which century or in
which Millennium the first Millennium
the second Millennium when was it
secondly
where exactly in which city-state did
democracy arise if they don't have the
questions you need to tell them to
please go and instead of giving opinions
find some simple facts easily uh you
know discoverable facts in which city
state that did democracy arise and then
the question is what form did this
democracy take
where women allowed to vote
where all citizens adult citizens
allowed to vote or where only men
allowed to vote and if women were not
allowed to vote only men were allowed to
vote then which men were allowed to vote
which what section of the adult male
population had a say in elections
was it every male or maybe where there
was a significantly large slave
population excluded from that
if you have slavery are you a democracy
by the way a nation which has slavery
can you call it a democracy
slaves have no rights including the
right to property the right to privacy
the right to life slaves are no right a
nation which practices slavery can never
ever ever ever ever be called a
democracy please get that through our
heads first of all
the definition of democracy is that the
entire adult population gets the right
to vote and stand in elections also
that's the simplest definition of
democracy it's more nuanced than that
but this is the simplest you know this
is how you would explain democracy to a
five-year-old
that the entire adult population male as
well as female Etc have the right not
only to vote but to stand for election
was this the case in Greece
slaves there was a significant slave
population they did not have the right
to vote or the right to life they could
be killed any time and there was no
crime killing a slave you know
secondly among the non-slaved males of
you know if you exclude the slaves and
include you exclude the women and you
exclude the you know children then you
have a certain population stratum of
population left which is adult males who
are not slaves now among them did they
all have the right to vote or where only
the rich and privileged people allowed
to vote so if you ask if you if you ask
yourself these questions and you look
for the answers all the answers
available online you just need to do a
Google search and search in the right
places don't search in blogs look look
up authoritative texts
look up texts written by the ancient
Greeks themselves it's all available
online all the translations in English
are available online look it up
here's the truth about democracy in
Greece only
wealthy land owning
males who came from certain families
were allowed to vote and and stand in
elections that's how it was in Greece it
was a horrifically in egalitarian
society a slave owning Society a society
in which women were second-class
citizens this is the truth
this is the truth look it up online look
up what the Greeks wrote about this
matter themselves
so do you call this democracy I I don't
call this a democracy this is in no
shape or form a democracy
right
no
the mahajanapada system
was very very interesting way it existed
way before Greece was even you know a
thought in anyone's mind so it predates
Greece by millennia
and we don't quite know
the exact system in which voting was
done but first of all it's way older
than Greece
way way older than Greece I mean if you
look at your your romula thapas and
whoever else they will tell about 500 BC
that's what they will say it's a
complete lie
greatly predate Greece but if you look
at the
if you if you read these books and they
say certain things you have to ask
yourself a simple question
when the so-and-so imminent historian
makes a statement or a claim in their
book what evidence are they putting in
front of you to back up the claim so
when they claim that the mahajanapada
system was 500 dates back to 500 BC what
evidence do they present to back up this
opinion
typically you will see no opinion no no
evidence or
doctor dividends you know Cherry big
dividends so the fact is that first of
all the margin about the system was very
very very very very ancient way it is
essentially the the late Vedic Age that
we're talking about and I will not go
into the chronology of The Vedic Age how
old it is but it clearly is something
that was contemporaneous with the uh
Saraswati being in her prime the river
Saraswati being in a prime and the
Saraswati was last in her prime around
at least 6 000 years before today at
least
so that's The Vedic Age or the late
Vedic Age so that that's how ancient the
mahajanapada system is and we have other
pieces of evidence also
um
and we don't know exactly what system we
had for voting and all but the uh system
of of electing your your rulers and
representatives in your local officials
is very very ancient in India
so that itself tells you that democracy
is way older in India and democracy was
not even a thing in Greece because you
had slavery and women were excluded and
only wealthy privileged males from
certain families were allowed to vote or
stand for election in the case of India
we never had slavery and women were
never second class citizens and if you
look at the you know the archaeological
evidence from the Saraswati Hindu
Regional
and so many other cities that we have
found you find that all the dwellings
are the same if it's a very egalitative
Society there is no evidence of
inequality there is no evidence of of
kings and rulers and Emperors so that
that itself tells you how egalitarian
and and maybe Democratic the society was
so we obviously would need more evidence
from but all the evidence that we have
already tells us that India was way more
egalitarian and Democratic than Greece
ever was in India democracy in India way
predates even the birth of Greece itself
so at the end of the day it's it's about
whether you want to trust people's
opinions that yeah or whether you want
to do a little bit of hard work and
respect yourself and look for the
evidence yourself
most of us are you know thinking is hard
work thinking is really hard most of us
just want to be taught what to think and
we will happily think that way but if
you want to go against the flow and
actually discover things from yourself
and with the understanding that much of
what we are told could be
not entirely true then it takes a lot of
hard work to go and look for the
evidence yourself do your own research
find the sources and the texts that your
teachers in the professors won't tell
you about even though it's all available
online it takes some work to do that and
most people for most people this doing
that work is too hard it's too difficult
it's it's much easier to live a
comfortable happy life in which you
believe that everything your teachers
tell you is right and that's how it is
all right right right right right okay
okay let's see some other questions
[Music]
um
hardik Sharma says in the movie
Passengers I saw that a spaceship was
running through nuclear reactor in it
while all passengers were hibernating
what are the problems in doing that in
real life first of all
hibernation humans don't hibernate bears
hibernate you go to the Himalayas you
have these giant bears you have how many
species of bears do we have in India at
least four or five species we have the
the brown bear the largest bear no the
second largest bear in the world is the
brown bear which is found across Eurasia
even in North America the the brown bear
we have that we have the Himalayan black
bear we have the sloth bear we have a
certain species of bear that is found in
the eastern part of into the Far East or
the so-called Northeast of India so we
have at least four species of bears in
India and typically the Bears that live
in cold regions where it gets really
cold and it freezes over in Winter those
Bears typically hibernate several months
a year what that means is that they eat
a huge amount of food in the summer time
in the springtime starting from
Springtime all the way into Autumn and
then as it starts getting low cold they
find a nice comfortable sheltered place
to go and sleep in and then they sleep
the entire winter
and to to be able to survive the entire
winter without eating they put on a huge
amount of weight during the preceding
months yeah and by the time winter is
over and spring comes out and they come
emerge from their cave or whatever it is
out of hibernation they are like it's
literally half the weight because the
body used up all that extra built up fat
um to sustain itself to keep the energy
to keep the metabolism going yeah fat is
a wonderful source of energy
so to hibernate
means
hibernation the word hibernation comes
from the uh the French word is Iver
which means winter so it's it's related
to that so it's about spending the
winter in the state of suspended
animation not being awake sleep sleep
several months four five months
to be able to do that you need
significant stores of energy fuel in the
body now human beings I mean unless you
you so if a human being were to
hibernate you would either have to put
on a huge amount of fat first or you
would need a system that would you know
keep on injecting energy either in the
form of glucose or something else into
the body so that while you're asleep uh
you you the body has enough fuel to uh
keep the metabolism going properly and
normally the second thing is how does
one hibernate I think one has to rewire
some parts of the brain to be able to
hibernate because typically human beings
sleep eight hours between six to eight
or six to nine hours a day on average I
would say
mostly it's around eight hours but it's
impossible even if you try to sleep
let's say 24 hours I think it's
extremely hard to sleep that long
um
did did our ancestors hibernate in the
past I don't see I don't know if there
is any evidence of that but we are
mammals after all
bears are also mammals there are other
animals also that hibernate so it may be
possible to you know rewire the brain or
do something that would induce
hibernation in human beings that's
number one or secondly you know
sometimes you have to medically put
people in in artificial Comas to give
them the time to recover when they have
they're injured or something especially
when some people get you know
cranial injuries head injuries and the
the the cerebrum cerebellum of the brain
is kind of slightly damaged or slightly
swollen
it makes sense to give the person a
couple of weeks of rest you know put
them in an induced coma so that uh the
the brain gets the time to you know uh
recover
so that is you could call it in some
sense artificial induced hibernation but
it's actually a Cuba which is done by
you know giving certain drugs and
injecting them into the bloodstream so
first of all the problem is that I I as
far as I know there is no way of
inducing hibernation in human beings as
far as I know the the research is being
done has been done and I'm sure it's
still being done maybe there could be a
breakthrough maybe we are close to a
breakthrough maybe we may already
perhaps possibly have the technology I
am not aware of it so number one the
problem is hibernation
the second thing is you know a cryo
sleep or whatever you you cool the body
down to a significant you know like 10
degrees below normal or whatever then
your metabolism really slows down so
that is something that could also be
done but these are all untested
Technologies you typically don't want to
test them on humans so you will have to
experiment with uh with
innocent animals and we know what
happens in that that's a different story
so the first thing is hibernation
is is not something that that is natural
to humans and I'm not sure if we can at
this point in time induce hibernation
safely and brings human bring human
beings out of hibernation safely after
say a month or three months or maybe 10
years or whatever it is the Journey of
the spaceship will last
uh nuclear reactor
spaceships using a nuclear reactor well
yeah you can you can certainly use a
nuclear reactor on a spaceship either to
generate the electricity to sustain to
keep all the systems going when it comes
to nuclear propulsion it's also possible
it solves the possible uh significant
amounts of research have been done in
the 19 I think 60s 70s perhaps about
possibly going to Mars using nuclear
propulsion essentially nuclear
explosions yeah it's certainly possible
but once you're out into space and
you've achieved the velocity that you
wanted to achieve you don't really need
a nuclear proportion engine going on all
the time you achieve your the velocity
you want and then you shut off the
engines you'll keep going that's
Newton's third law of motion uh Second
Law whichever it is you know third law
is action and reaction opposites I think
it's the second law of motion we're
talking about the first which one look
it up so once you achieve
your velocity you cannot keep on going
with that velocity in the same direction
unless you're acted upon by an external
Force
so uh
and I'm sure there are more efficient
ways of uh achieving High velocities one
example one one technology is the solar
cell technology
um or light sail technology in which you
have a large sale light sale very thin
sale in which on which you shine in
normal enormous amounts of laser light
using that you can accelerate a
spacecraft to tremendous velocities
maybe like 10 20 30 of the speed of
light in about half an hour
so that's enough so you don't need
nuclear propulsion for that once once
you've achieved that velocity but it is
certainly possible yeah the problems in
real life let's see first of all nuclear
reactors are reasonably safe are
actually very safe compared to other
things if you if you design it properly
you build it properly it's going to be
very safe so nuclear reactors are not
problematic uh so that's fine the only
issue I see in this entire thing is
hibernation I'm not sure
the it is it is achievable it may be but
I'm not I don't I'm pretty sure we still
don't have the ability to safely induce
hibernation make a person hibernate for
certain amount of time and then bring
that person out of hibernation safely I
don't think it's ever been done so yeah
that's that's what I can say
okay so Mahesh says where was The Vedic
were the people of The Vedic period
vegetarian or non-vegetarian look
India is enormous huge some subcontinent
sized
uh territory it's a subcontinent it's
not a nation state the little one
enormous so we had an enormous diversity
of people and in The Vedas we have for
instance if you see that you know the
relevant sections for the ashram
you at the end of the ashram you
sacrifice the horse yeah you sacrifice
him and then
you you eat the Flesh of the horse
ritually ritualistically and there's
more to it I'll not go into that
right so uh this was thousands of years
ago
there seems to be evidence of people
eating meat and I'm sure lots of people
will get offended is because I'm saying
this right now
because we try to project what we are
today into the past into our ancestors
you know
it may be right or wrong but some people
say that the past is a different country
it's a different time in different place
and the customers may have been very
different now we know we have cultural
continuity over thousands of years and
we know that overall in our culture it
is said that being
non-violent is the highest ideal and
which means you should be vegetarian and
not cause any unnecessary cruelty but I
don't think it was uniformly you know
practiced everywhere I am sure there
were people maybe significant person
sections of the population that ate meat
even Lord Buddha who was the epitome of
non-violence and ahinsa it is said that
his last meal on the planet Earth was a
dish made of pork
he he he attained he attained
mahaparindra Nirvana In the City of
kushinagar
discourse the last sermon that he gave
which is extremely instructive and most
people want to kind of forget it because
it's very inconvenient
but uh okay that's a different story but
yeah his last meal was supposed to be a
dish of pork
so I think Indians have always been in
two camps
one Camp is the vegetarian camp we will
not cause any unnecessary cruelty and we
will eat only you know plant-based food
or maybe maybe Dairy also and there was
always one Camp most likely that the the
maybe the the ones who were warriors Etc
they would need more protein and that's
what that's why they had a more thomasic
diet
so uh so I can't say for sure but there
are elements in The Vedic texts that do
hint at people consuming meat so don't
hate me for this this is just what I've
seen and let's not get emotional about
these things we may be a certain way
today it doesn't mean that our ancestors
were the same way several thousand years
ago right
okay
uh right
um
AI let's talk about EI in the human
brain transhumanism vikrant says so your
latest episode on TRS yeah it's a very
long episode wonderful right good fun I
had good fun recording that so with
ranveer always fun talking to him
the question neurologists have already
mapped the human brain and thoughts are
neurons firing electric signals will AI
be able to mimic the human brain okay so
interesting question we have mapped the
human brain uh neurologists and
Physicians and doctors and anatomists
have spent countless hours uh working on
cadavers which is you know dead human
bodies that have been donated for
medical science or whatever
let's not go into how they procure these
things
and then you know even in the case of
Albert Einstein his brain was removed
and it was diced up into cubes and they
are still being studied apparently
and they still haven't been able to
decipher what was so special about him
so listen that itself is a good example
doctors have preserved Albert Einstein's
brain one of the greatest scientists in
the history of humanity nobody disputes
that now the greatest Geniuses of all
time
his brain has been preserved it has been
diced up small cubes have been made and
scientists have been studying these
portions of his brain for decades and
they have not been able to decipher or
discern or discover what made him
special
so we may have mapped the human brain we
know the anatomy of the human brain we
know all the sections we know what
nerves go where we have the optic nerve
that crosses itself behind the eyes you
know it it crosses itself and it goes
like that so it's not this eye goes in
this direction the nerve and this the
nerve for this eye goes there the optic
nerves cross over there this is a
conjunction point and then they go in
that direction into the brain so the
eyes actually are an extension of the
brain so we know and we understand the
different parts of the brain and we have
a very good idea of how the connections
are and what what processing happens in
which section we also know that neurons
fire and that's how these trillions of
connections are formed and that's maybe
what gives rise to the human mind or
Consciousness and all that yeah and it's
still we don't instill we don't
understand
we understand next to nothing about the
human mind human thoughts
we can certainly you know put new we put
electrodes on the human brain human
scalp and
figure out the brain activity which
portions of the brain are active when
you're doing certain activities let's
say when you're reading or when you're
playing music when you're singing when
you're just thinking or when you're
sleeping there are different modes of
brain activity
um different kinds of waves alpha waves
waves beta waves Etc we know a lot about
the brain and we still know next to
nothing about it the best example of
that of not knowing understanding the
brain is that you have Einstein's brain
which is disassembled and chopped up
into cubes and we still don't know what
made him a genius what what is special
about this brain as opposed to the brain
of a different person we still don't
know uh and there are animals that have
much larger brains than human beings
much larger brains the elephant's brain
is much larger than ours
I'm sure many whales have much larger
brains than humans so what makes us
different from them why are they not way
more intelligent than us or maybe is it
the fact that their bodies are different
from ours and that they're confined in
the water or whatever that that gives
them
that kind of shackles them
they don't have fingers and the tools to
to modify the world there are lots of
questions so yeah it is possible that
thoughts are maybe lots of neurons
working in tandem firing signals you
know the we know how neurons work the
sodium so you know ions and all that I
mean you can look it up it's very
interesting so so that's so we know a
lot and we still don't know a lot that's
that's the situation we are in we still
don't understand Consciousness at all
yeah so we may create we may be able to
create neural network that mimics the
human brain you know uh neural networks
like gpd3 Etc are one could make the
claim that they have already passed the
Turing test you can't really tell if
it's a human being or a machine on the
other other end that you're talking to
it's we've already reached that that
stage
so it can mimic human activity
there is this a thought experiment in in
philosophy it's called philosophical
zombies or something in which the the
thing is that if you have
if you have an artificial machine
artificial brain that acts just like a
human being you see the same responses
does it mean it's conscious or is it
just pretending is it just an imitation
machine
right so it's it's it goes to the root
of Consciousness what Consciousness is
so I think AI will be able to mimic the
human brain
but I don't know if it will ever be
conscious the way we are conscious
we may not be able to tell the
difference it will behave exactly the
way a human being would behave
and still we will not know whether it's
conscious when it comes to biological
creatures we know consciousness
we we recognize that the moment we see
it you see a cat you know there's
Consciousness there that kind of is
conscious each cat is unique each cat
has a different character uh personality
same with dogs same with elephants same
with horses same with tigers same with
lions
um same with whales Etc so we recognize
Consciousness when we say but we can't
define it
so will AI be the same if you have
different disi systems will they all
have their own personalities
you know distinct personalities is is
that something that will emerge and if
it does emerge does it still mean that
this system is conscious
so there is a research that has been
done by Dr Sebastian you know who has
been researching this extensively he
says it is never going to be possible
for an AI system to be fully conscious
the way human beings are conscious it
simply lacks certain things
um I will not elaborate on that right
now because it's a very detailed piece
of research but you can look up the
paper online so I think AI will be able
to mimic
human beings maybe mimic the human brain
but I don't know if it will ever
actually be conscious but it doesn't
mean it could not be dangerous or
powerful
AIS could become super intelligent way
more powerful and capable than human
beings are
you know
that could happen but it may still not
be conscious
that's the deal okay okay okay where are
we now let's take some more questions I
I
um
writer word says what do you think of
the internet does it have bad effects on
humans does internet is human internet
making humans less productive and more
anxious yes it it all depends on how you
use it for most people social media is
all it's social media is designed to
hook you in to draw you in and to
Captivate you for hours on end you keep
scrolling scrolling scrolling no it
keeps on giving you this dopamine
release every time because once it
understands what kind of videos you
watch or what what kind of texts or
posts you you're interested in it will
give you more of the same
so it it's you know they've really
figured out human psychology really well
that's where the real sociology of the
world is happening you know in these
corporations they understand sociology
and human psychology way better than
your your professors do your professors
are amateurs Now by this point you know
they may have written these wonderful
books and they may look very
distinguished and eminent
but it's the real psychology and the
real sociology is happening in this big
Corporation they've really figured out
the human psyche and psychology and they
really know how to hook you in
especially when you are very young they
have kids today who are hooked on to
these things you know teenagers and even
12 years old and 10 years old kids and
all that and adults as well and one and
over time you realize you're wasting
your time but you're so hooked to it and
that kind of makes you feel great it
gives you the short-term dopamine
release Joy feeling of pleasure while
long term making you more anxious and
more worried and it I'm sure people get
depressed by this
so it's up to you it's your choice you
can you know it's it's about it's about
having a personal policy it's as simple
as that make your own policy of how much
time you will spend on the internet
especially in social media internet is
fine
you can use the internet for doing
research for studying for discovering
things for a lot of good work it's
social media that's the problem
social media especially the short tiny
little videos
yeah I'm not saying all tiny videos are
bad but typically when you see these
reels endlessly
cat videos or or whatever videos it is
it can be genuinely
big distraction and a brain on your time
so have a policy formulate a policy I
will spend x amount of time per day on
social media once that time is done uh
it's done I'll not look at it if you can
have that much
that modicum of discipline you're good
but if you are gonna be a slave to to
the algorithms then you're gonna waste
your time you're gonna waste your life
it's gonna make you less productive way
less productive it's going to make you
very sedentary and you're gonna get more
and more anxious so that's that's
essentially it's your choice
will you be the master of the devices
that you own or will the devices be your
Masters yeah I think the internet is a
wonderful tool the internet has brought
Humanity together it's It's Made It One
Planet one one Society for a change we
have very different people but we're all
together we all have these common
meeting grounds you know social media
so it's something that has empowered
people I mean for for when it comes to
India it's brought the people of India
together for the first time in a
millennium it's given the ordinary man
woman and child of India a voice for the
first time in a thousand years
India India has been suppressed for a
thousand years now finally social media
has given everybody a voice
we can now connect in real time with
people across the length and the breadth
of India and the entire world so that is
empowering that's wonderful but then if
you get drawn into it hooked into it and
you know you become uh
you're part of the Matrix like like the
movie you know Keanu Reeves then yeah
it's not going to be good for you so it
has its good points and bad points it's
up to you how you want to use it
so as long as you have a clear policy of
how you will use the internet
you know take a couple of hours take
take a day off from the internet and
think about how you know we want to use
it and write it down these many hours
I'll spend on the internet out of which
This Much Time on social media and
that's it
and you'll be good to go all right
um
says what I thought on Darwin's theory
being removed from ncrd class 10th books
uh
I I'm I I keep hearing about this I have
not really looked into what they've done
or not assuming that what the reports
are saying is correct and they've
removed Darwin's theory of evolution
from class 10th books
well the question is have they put it in
class nine books already or has it been
moved to class 11th I don't care at what
point in time you teach it as long as
you teach it and it's not Darwin's
theory
maybe some people have an issue with
this guy Darwin it's just Evolution and
evolution is a thing so if you don't if
you are teaching kids biology but you
don't want to teach Evolution that is
problematic so I don't know whether that
is the case
maybe possibly hypothetically I don't
know but maybe they're teaching it at a
different point in time then what's
wrong with that
the education uh the people in charge of
the education system have the
the right to make certain choices as to
when to to introduce what concepts in in
the the syllabus in the curriculum
I'm sure you can teach the theory of
evolution to a 10 year old I'm sure you
can if you know how to communicate and
teach
it's not that hard
so I don't know what's being done I have
not really looked into it um
but if they are if if it is so like some
people are claiming that they are
completely expunging the curriculum at
all levels of the theory of fibration
that would be problematic but I'm not
sure if that is the case
I I
am a firm you know I mean I am
very Pro science I'm a scientist right I
believe that a nation can progress only
if we Embrace Science and Technology but
of course we have to keep it in Balance
by being rooted in our culture
there is no clash between culture and
Science and Technology some people claim
it those people are I don't know which
polite word you could use for them but
yeah some very intelligent people claim
that you cannot be culturally grounded
by also being scientifically Advanced so
you have to choose one or the other that
is an over simplistic
uh take I would say
um so I think that uh we have to teach
all aspects of science proven science we
know that evolution is a thing we see
that in the fossil record over millions
of years
so this has to be taught at what level
let them decide but if it is being
completely removed that would be a
problem that's what I that's my view
okay
says I'm a ba Chinese student
interesting I read from Cambridge
University books I borrow from the
library is there there are they are
12 000 rupees per Book for a series of
18 and I other I read other western
books won't they contain biases as they
do for India
you read any
book that's written by Western authors
or Indian authors
um you will you will it is inevitable
that it will contain a eurocentric or
occidentalist bias
uh Edward said called it orientalism the
way they you know they they
um
they subtly or sometimes overtly
disparage Eastern cultures and portray
them as as primitive in subtle ways
sometimes old ways in the case of china
it's more subtle in the case of India
it's like complete demonization of
everything of everything Indian
uh so if you are reading Cambridge
University books about China I can
promise you I can guarantee you it's
gonna contain
eurocentric and occidentalist bias I
think China is a wonderful civilization
it's three three and a half thousand
years old and India and China have had
great relations I I think China's
civilization is wonderful there's a
great amount of beauty and richness in
their culture one very interesting
history as well and the books that we
get to read about China are all written
by westerners I would like to see a
history of China and studies of Chinese
culture written by Chinese and
translated into Maybe
maybe English perhaps but translated by
Chinese into English then
you will know that this is a proper
Chinese perspective because the it is
a culture can be represented properly
only by people who belong to that
culture not by Outsiders who know next
to nothing about it even if a person has
a PHD in Chinese culture and has spent
20 years researching Chinese culture
that person still doesn't understand
Chinese culture properly or Indian
culture for that matter Outsiders will
never understand
a culture properly
it's only people who are born in that
culture that truly understand that
culture so you know so so if you're
reading Cambridge University books it's
it's a guarantee that it will contain
biases now it's up to you to be alert
when you're reading you can certainly
read that I mean there are it's a series
of 18 books wow that's a big Series yeah
uh so I'm sure there's a lot of good
information in there but you have to be
mentally alert when you're reading
everything so yeah it takes time and
practice to reach that level of maturity
and alertness where you can tell when
somebody is being biased you know and
the best way to to to uh
the best way to misrepresent a culture
in a book
is to measure that 98 of what you write
is accurate in this two percent
misinformation in there very subtly
mixed in so you really can't tell and
that's the best you know that's the most
effective way of of misleading people 98
of what you write has to be accurate
just two percent has to be
misinformation and you mix it in very
subtly so you have to be really alert
when you read these books so yes the
short answer is they will certainly
contain bias anti-china bias as they do
for India
um
okay
what's your thoughts about the
Philadelphia Experiment says Abhishek is
involvement of Albert Einstein true I
have seen no evidence of any involvement
of Albert Einstein in any experiments he
was a theoretical physicist it's a pure
theoretical physicist which means that
his laboratory was his brain and
the other lab so all you need to be a
theoretical physicist is your brain your
mind independent paper that's all you
need and these as you did the internet
for research and all that but that's it
you don't Tinker with machines and do
stuff and all that yeah so Einstein was
a pure theoretical physicist he I don't
know of him ever doing any experiments
apart from thought experiments he was
great at thought experiments experiments
so as far as I am as I know I am 99.99
convinced that albertanso has no
involvement whatever in this alleged
Philadelphia Experiment
um and I don't know if it actually
happened I mean there are all kinds of
stories that are out there of people
getting embedded in the in the in the
walls of a ship and all that well show
me the evidence it's not something that
happens on a routine basis
and we don't want the technology to make
that happen in case the U.S government
has such technology well that's that's
technology that kind of bends the laws
of physics as we know them so my
thoughts about the Philadelphia
Experiment is that it's most likely I'm
very strongly almost convinced that it's
it's uh urban legend or a myth that has
been made up by people to sell books or
or to get famous or whatever I don't I
don't think it really happened yeah
because from everything I understand of
Science and physics such things can't
happen obviously I can be wrong we only
understand five percent of the universe
so obviously I can be wrong but from
what I know it's it's something that's
most likely just a myth or a legend and
Einstein had no involvement in any
experiment as far as I know in his life
he was a pure bred theoretical physicist
all right
uh yeah
um
let's see this
I'm a photographer says Kunal well while
I was out in a wildlife Wildlife
Sanctuary for astrophotography I saw a
UFO and I have got it on raw files okay
I know what I have in my hard drive I
know what I saw well
put it out in the public domain
I I I've heard of people who have who
have witnessed UFOs I personally
I personally don't remember if I have
witnessed a UFO if I had I would try to
come to my mind immediately but I know
of people who have witnessed phenomena
aerial phenomena that are not easily
explainable and some of them have taken
photographs of that or video so if you
have done this please put it out in the
public domain not the raw file but the
PNG or whatever
and put it out on social media put it
out on Twitter tag me in it or put it on
Instagram or whatever tag me if I can
find it I get I don't know millions of
notifications per day but I will try to
look for it so please do that and let's
let's see how it goes let's see what it
looks like
often you will have natural phenomena
that appear like UFOs there is something
called lenticular clouds that look like
flying saucers
I'm not saying I'm not claiming that
what you have seen may or may not be
this or that I'm just saying that often
you will find natural phenomena that
look very suspicious uh
you also have these starlink satellites
these days that look very strange to a
person who's not aware of the presence
of Starling satellites in the sky this
entire line of satellites that going by
it at a reasonably leisurely Pace across
the sky so if you are aware of Starling
it will be no nothing new to you but
otherwise it's going to be very you know
uh
disconcerting so I would say that you
know if you have this on your on your
hard drive please process it please make
a PNG or whatever out of it jpg whatever
works for you and put it out on social
media and let's take a look
all right
okay uh
uh all right let's go uh Veer Singh
yadav says what are my views on the
Chinese president Mr XI jinpig's
upcoming visit to India in the coming
months can the relations improve I said
that India and China relations are can
only improve from where they are right
now I mean we are not at War but we have
significant tensions along the uh
undemarkated boundary between India and
Tibet the Chinese occupied Tibet and
they are trying to encroach into Indian
Territory India is now building
infrastructure at Breakneck speed along
the border
the Border roads organization bro
you go to London it's you'll see these
bro signs everywhere bro bro welcomes
you I'm like who's bro unless you know
so India is building infrastructure into
tremendous space
Railways roads mostly Bridges Etc and
that has disconcerted China because now
India's infrastructure is is is coming
up to where it should be air scripts
Landing scripts much more
so um
so that's been the cause of tensions and
that's why the Chinese have been trying
to provoke India so I think the
relations between India and China can
only improve from where they are right
now the Chinese will not try to start a
war with India because it can escalate
in any unforeseen Direction and when you
have two Nuclear Power nuclear-armed
Nations you don't want to go to war and
you don't want to risk the chance of a
escalation escalation
so I think that India and China
relations can only go upwards
from now from where they are today it's
good to know that Mr XI is coming to
India what exactly is the event I'm not
sure is it the
is it the G20 thing is it the SEO thing
is it the bricks thing I think brics is
in South Africa something is coming up
and it's good that he's coming to India
uh I think there's a huge amount of
potential for India and China and also
Russia
in in terms of cooperation
if we can find a proper negotiated and
fair solution
to the Border issue
which will need some give and take from
both sides for sure
if we can do that if we can achieve that
then there will be no more tensions
hopefully along the border
which should be fully demarcated and
then India and China's relationship can
actually
cautiously one could say improve
significantly especially when one puts
Russia into the mix see right now what
we are seeing is a bifurcation of the
global World Order
for 500 years we have had the
Anglo-Saxon hegemony over the world more
or less
they have been ruling the world they
have been dictating terms the so-called
rules-based World Order which was based
on their whims and fancies it's been an
extremely exploitative system that has
uh served to strengthen and enrich them
at the expense of the rest of the world
if we may not see it that way but do you
understand how much their Indian rupee
has devalued since 1947.
there was a time when one rupee was
roughly equal to one dollar what is it
now 80.
imagine India's rupees even at 10 10
Rupees to a dollar India's GDP would be
eight times what it is today
so I think it is it is a good thing that
the world order is is realizing
significantly and it can happen only if
the three large great powers can
cooperate India and Russia and China and
if if one is out of this mix it's going
to be it's not going to work
if they really want to create a new and
more fair and Equitable World Order and
to finally put an end to the Anglo-Saxon
hegemony of the world for that these
three great Powers have no option but to
work together
so I think the the weakest link in this
grouping in brics is China because of
their hegemonic and expansionist and
imperialistic policies
and I think it's time for China to wake
up and smell the coffee of how things
are going
it's very clear now that this is going
to be the Indian Century most Indians
will not agree with me because they see
look around and this is
wait wait wait until 2013 and see where
India is
so
the Chinese are not stupid they will
know how things are going and what
direction the world is going they will
obviously keep on working to to towards
making the nation more powerful why not
they have the right to do it everything
against that but it cannot come at the
expense of India that's something they
have to understand and that's what the
Indian government has I think proved has
has done more than enough to demonstrate
to China that it's it's not going to
work for you if you try to mess with
India so I think there has to be some
kind of compromise or some kind of
solution to this
the ideal situation is we demarcate the
boundary in a fair just Equitable manner
with some give and take possibly on both
sides yep if you do that then things
will be better and then India and China
and Russia can work together to really
create a proper good just fair equitable
system that is apart from the
Anglo-Saxon hegemonic system that we
have experienced with the past 500 years
and because we have lived under the
system for 500 years we don't see
anything wrong with it most of us
if you unless you go deep into it and
see what they're doing you know to
exploit everybody else so I think it's a
very good sign that Mr XI is coming to
India obviously he will be in
consideration with Prime Minister Modi
and other leaders but it's mainly about
India and China from my perspective uh
the relations need to improve it's going
to be good for India as well as for
China and for much of the global South
the so-called Global South
which is Africa and East Asia in
Southeast Asia and to some extent Latin
America
that's the global South the Nations that
have been that have been groaning under
the the heavy boot of colonialism for
almost five centuries half a millennium
it's high time we end this nonsense
so that can only happen if Ric happens
and it's still a fair way away you know
it's still a little early to start
talking about that so Mr Modi and Mr she
need to get together work things out I
think Mr XI understands this so it's a
good thing he's coming and I I am
hopeful I'm hopeful I am hopeful that
things will improve between India and
China it will be good for both Nations
and for the peoples of both countries
om says is it possible to make
nuclear-powered c-130j like aircraft
let's let's look at the c-130g what does
the c-130j look like see a 130j it's a
heavy lift Transport Aircraft not heavy
lift medium lift uh let's put that on
the screen
so this is what the Google image search
tells us here it is
that's what it looks like it's a
reasonably large aircraft as you can see
we can see it with people there you have
it
it's an American built aircraft and the
Indian Air Force operates many of these
super Hercules aircraft it's a
reasonably large aircraft there are
larger there are bigger ones as well
aircraft that are bigger than this one
and it's a it's an old actually it's an
aircraft that's been in service for a
very long time for decades so so that's
the size that we're talking about can
you have an aircraft like that powered
by a nuclear propulsion
well we already have nuclear-powered
cruise missiles the Russians have a
nuclear power Cruise which can
essentially loiter around the earth for
indefinitely days possibly weeks
so if you can use the same kind of
propulsion in this aircraft
let's say see this this aircraft is a
has turboprop engines propellers as you
can see
uh as you can see this propellers over
here so you take this aircraft and you
replace the four propellers with let's
say two nuclear uh propulsion systems or
maybe four nuclear property systems or
maybe even one I don't know depending on
the strength power of that
it can certainly work the question is
how safe is it
planes can crash and if you have a
nuclear reactor or four nuclear reactors
on your plane
your plane crashes it's going to be an
environmental catastrophe
when it comes to cruise missiles they're
anyway designed to crash and be
destroyed when it comes to planes you
don't ever want them to crash but
unfortunately sometimes accidents happen
they happen
they happen from time to time
so that's the reason why I think the
Americans have tried this in the 1960s
or something 50 60 70 somewhere around
that time nuclear proposition nuclear
reactor on an aircraft
I think it certainly can work
so you can have a miniaturized nuclear
uh reactor
which can possibly
run a turboprop engine the way possibly
like what you have in submarines that
also has this uh you know propeller at
the end
helical propeller or you can have
nuclear power but a nuclear scramjet or
Ramjet for instance in which instead of
fuel it is a nuclear reaction that that
uh that uh raises the temperature of the
air to the extent that you have the the
Ramjet effect or or scramjet effect so
you can have nuclear powered Ram Jets
which would which would make this a
Hypersonic plane actually you know
supersonic plane so it's possible but
it's dangerous because planes do crash
from time to time one never wants them
to crash but they do rush and if a plane
crashes with a nuclear reactor on board
it's going to be in one environmental
disaster so that's why nobody has done
this also nuclear reactors are heavy
and fossil fuel engines are much lighter
so that's the reason why it's never been
done but it's certainly possible
um
right
okay what do we have what do we have
what else what else
um Sanjeev says if India can't opt for
one child policy like China what can be
some alternatives to control such a
drastic blast of population so that's an
interesting question so India's
population has now surpassed that of
China India's population is 1.4 billion
or 140 crores like we say in sankrit or
Hindi 140 crores
now
ideally we have to ask ourselves what is
the ideal size of the population of the
Indian subcontinent we're talking about
the Indian subordinary which includes
Afghanistan Pakistan Nepal Bangladesh
Sri Lanka Bhutan all of that let's talk
about all of that Maldives
what's the ideal size of the Indian
subcontinence population well around the
beginning
of the 20th century let's say around
1930 1940 what was the population it was
about 330 million
33 crores
right today it is 140 crores
so I think ideally the population of
India the Indian subcontinent should be
between 300 to 350 million and we are
way past that so obviously when you have
like four times roughly four times the
population
when you have roughly four times the
ideal population there's gonna be a huge
burden on the resources of the
subcontinent
on the soil
on on the natural resources so you will
have four times the ideal amount of
people competing for the same resources
it's gonna place a huge burden
on the systems on the infrastructure and
on the resources it's gonna cause
uh deforestation is going to cause the
soil quality to to deteriorate it's
gonna cause Extinction of species
unfortunately
it's it has all the terrible effects so
ideally you want the population of India
to gradually slowly sustainably shrink
over an extended period of time
to around 350 million or so that I would
say should happen over the next two or
three centuries not over the next 50
years which would be a total disaster
why will it be a disaster because when
you shut down the birth rate
the total fertility rate for a sustained
population of the same same population
is 2.1 children per woman
that's the
TFR total fertility rate for sustaining
the population at the current level
if you want the population to start
dropping it should the TFR should be
below 2.1 right now India's TFR is 2.0
so we are already below sustainable uh
below sustainable population so India's
population will slowly decline China's
TFR is around one is around 1.1 which is
a catastrophe and when your population
starts declining and the birth rate
decreases you know what happens the
average age of the population starts
rising and soon China's population by
2050 is going to be the average age will
be 57 or 58. when your average human
being is 58 years old what Vitality will
your nation have ask yourselves this
if you opt for a one child policy in 30
40 50 years that's that's the situation
where you're going to encounter
and there's almost no coming back from
there even if China forces its
population to have a three child policy
it is still not going to make much of an
impact now for the next hundred years or
so
that's the conundrum they have put
themselves in
so the alternative for India I agree
that the population needs to come down
the ideal population should be between
300 to 350 million which is almost
one-fourth of where we are today
one fourth yeah one quarter
you to to come down to that level you
have to do it in a very gradual slow
steady calibrated and intelligent manner
otherwise your average age is gonna your
average age is going to rise and you're
going to have a nation of old people
in such a nation can't survive for the
long term so ideally I would say this
this should happen over the next two
centuries at least a century even a
century is too much it's too little I
would say it should be over the next two
cents by 2200
ideally India's population should be
around 354 or 400 million or maybe 300
million even that may be a little little
too drastic perhaps maybe three
centuries so there is no short-term
solution to this short short-term
Solutions are never good
so that's the alternative I can think of
it has to be done in a very intelligent
calibrated and very gradual manner
ideally the average age of your
population should be below 40.
should be below 40. so by 2050 India's
average age is going to be about 37 or
38. ideally you want it to be in in the
early 30s or even late 20s that's that's
a strong vital younger population that's
how you want to be you don't want
everyone to be old
so that's uh that's what I would say
should happen a one child policy is is
terrible maybe a two-child policy for a
start maybe a two-time policy
and I'm sure there'll be lots of
protests if you do that but well okay
uh they just says is the Sphinx older
than the pyramids how can that be let's
let's look at the Springs Sphinx the
Sphinx is this figure right this lion
human figure
uh
the Sphinx let's put it on the screen
it's this uh
it's it's a lion with a face of a human
being
it's uh and no one really knows what its
age is if you look at it you can see
that it has suffered enormous amount
enormous amounts of erosion the sands of
time have eroded the structure away look
at the face it's damaged it's not
damaged because of erosion it's damaged
because of Napoleon's troops who used
the Sphinx face for target practice for
their cannons that's why the face is
damaged but if you look at this you can
see if you look at the body of the
Sphinx you can see the kind of erosion
you see on you know the kind of
geological erosion you see on the on
Mountain sides for instance in the
Western ghat in India which are some of
the oldest mountains in the world so
clearly this is a very ancient structure
and uh
some people would say that you should
carbonate these things you can't carbon
date minerals you can't carbonate rocks
you can only carbonate organic material
and this is pure rock so you can't
carbon date it and so that's why nobody
really knows how old it is so most
historians in this egyptologists I think
they claim it's uh about as old as the
pyramids but I would say that the
pyramids even though they have been
significantly damaged you can see all
the all the outer cladding has been
removed
yeah only the top portion is there so
even though the pyramids have been
significantly damaged over the past few
two Millennia they still seem to be in
better shape than the Sphinx
so I think the Sphinx could be way way
older than the pyramids maybe 5 000
years old maybe who knows how much older
I don't know because I don't have any
data
maybe this is how it looked uh in the
old days the pyramids look very
different in the old days they were very
smooth and shiny and pretty now they're
all ruined
so I think it's possible that the Sphinx
may be way older than the pyramids maybe
thousands of years older than the
pyramids but we don't know for sure we
don't know
all right
yeah I'm Aditya says what happened to
Queen samyukta after the death of
prithviraj Chauhan it is debated whether
the she committed johar was or was
updated by gory I don't quite know you
know the historical records are very
sketchy and very scarce and so my my
answer is I don't know I don't really
know what happened uh the best case
scenario is that she committed johar
you understand how horrible the
situation it was those days the best
case scenario is actually committed
johar and that was it so I don't really
know
um
okay
uh it was a lion face of the Sphinx yes
it was a lion face of the swings
Surya GitHub says your views on the
punch attack and what should India do
yes recently we had this condemnable
and unacceptable terrorist action in
which uh an Indian army Convoy was
attacked a vehicle was attacked in some
a number of Indian uh Armed Forces
Personnel lost their lives it is
condemnable it is unacceptable and
whoever has done this will be brought to
Justice now what should India do about
this
um
yeah well see
one what are the options that we have
one option is we teach the pakistanis
another big lesson
disproportionate retaliation
so you killed 504 guys we're gonna kill
10 times you guys you're terrorists
terrorists not civilians terrorists and
combatants which means uh army military
personnel that's one option
so it could be either in the form of a
surgical strike or a airstrike but now
the pakistanis know about this that
India could do this so what should India
do you know there's only
the the best way to respond to this is
to ensure that in the next three to five
years Pakistan is a thing of the past
that's what India has to do Pakistan is
teetering on the brink of economic
collapse it's being propped up by its
its overlords the Western Powers the IMF
the World Bank essentially the US
um
so
the I would say that the best way to
respond to this
is to ensure that we engineer the
peaceful
uh balkanization of Pakistan within the
next three to five years
even 10 years is too much now
and once again let me reiterate I have
nothing against the people of Pakistan
the I have nothing against the ordinary
man woman and child in Pakistan nothing
at all they're our own people they're
the same blood the same past but of
course they hate us today which is a
whole different story most of them I'm
not sure I don't think everyone hates us
in India
Indians
I don't think every Pakistani hates
India or Indians but most of them we
know they do but I have nothing against
them
so it should happen ideally peacefully
without any shots fired
so that's what India should do ideally
but if it's not achievable peacefully we
can look at other Solutions with minimum
damage but uh you know Pakistan has been
bleeding India with U.S support for
decades
I don't think the most Ardent Pakistani
fan can deny this
or the most Ardent U.S fan can do others
the Americans have funded and financed
Pakistani terrorism in India for several
decades it stopped at some point in time
after 2008 I believe
but we don't know what the situation is
now
they they supported Al-Qaeda they
supported Osama Bin Laden they supported
Saddam Hussein they supported lots of
such people
you read the book which is called black
flags it will tell you that the
Americans even created Isis
uh so Pakistan is a proxy
which is designed to keep India off
balance now India has become too big for
Pakistan to keep us off balance
so um so ideally and and you know
Pakistan was created out of Indian
Territory without ever Consulting the
people of India it was a bunch of
politicians who were appointed by the
British who made who made this decision
it was actually a British decision to
balkanize India to break India up so uh
it is Indian Territory it is a territory
of our ancestors it was taken away from
us without our consent and in the long
term we will get it back nobody can stop
this but right now Pakistan needs to be
balkanized the the
just aspirations for freedom of the
people of Balochistan of the people of
Sindh or the people of Hyderabad of the
people of gilgit baltistan and Pakistan
Kashmir they need to you know these
aspirations need to be met
should be allowed to reintegrate itself
with Afghanistan
and poke need to come back to India
punjabistan can stay whatever it is
that's fine
so that's what needs to happen you know
in the next three to five years ideally
three years I'm sure it can be done we
are reaching that stage now so I think
instead of retaliating to individual
attacks this is what India should focus
on right now that's what I think should
happen
okay
uh ujjwal says please talk about current
relations between India and Israel
um
see we have to understand what Israel is
uh let's go to the screen because we're
talking about another Nation so we need
to uh
I'm sure most of us know where Israel is
but just in case some of us don't I'm
gonna put that on the map because as you
know I love the map
where is the map
here is the map
so Israel we know where India is go
westwards we move through
the temporary nation in Afghanistan then
Persia and then we move into the Middle
East
Iraq Syria Jordan and then we have
Israel Israel over here which is west of
Jordan north of Egypt and the Sinai
region this is Israel so relations so
Israel is is an outlier in the Middle
East it's it's maybe the only non-muslim
nation there today
uh Lebanon used to be a Christian Nation
but it is not so anymore because of a
demographic re-engineering which
happened in the
second half of the 20th century
so Israel is a Jewish Nation mostly
Jewish
the majority is Jewish it's an outlier
in the Middle East because all other
nations
are Islamic Nations Muslim nations
including turkey which is like some of
it is in Europe
and Israel has survived lots of
lots of very hairy situations multiple
Wars and it's it has survived because it
has see first of all the people of
Israel are very resilient their their
very resourceful Etc but it would not
have survived without the uh support of
the United States so you could consider
Israel to be essentially in some ways a
proxy of the U.S
in the Middle East region
uh now the relationship between India
and much of the Middle East is excellent
today
when it comes to Saudi Arabia India
Saudi Arabia relations are excellent
excellent today India UAE relations are
excellent India Oman relations are
excellent you know it's very surprising
but it's the case India has extremely
good relations with these nations when
it comes to Iran also we have a very
good understanding with them and now
what we are seeing is that the Nations
these nations are now uh
creating I mean they are now uh
normalizing so to say to some extent
their relationship with Israel so
historically it's been a very
antagonistic relationship but now there
many of them are establishing diplomatic
relations they are giving Israel or
flight or flight uh rights and much more
so it's a good thing overall
you know a couple of weeks ago we had
velina chakarova on on my podcast and
she made a very interesting observation
uh she said that the U.S influence in
the Middle East is declining
and the Middle East is stabilizing she I
think she made two separate statements
but one can certainly connect them
together that the Middle East is now
stabilizing significantly
while at the same time U.S influence is
decreasing it is clearly in this case a
case of cause and effect
it was the U.S influence in the Middle
East that was creating these horrible
crises the Middle East was always in in
crisis and now that the U.S influence is
declining the Middle East is stabilizing
and the nations are you know making up
with each other I mean the Saudis and
the Iranians have re-established
diplomatic relations which is a huge
step forward and so on so India and
Israel for the longest time we had a
covered relationship not an overt
relationship I don't think India even
recognized Israel as an established
diplomatic relations until sometime in
the 90s
and the first time an Indian leader
visited Israel was in the 2010s when Mr
Modi made his first trip to Israel but
overall India and Israel have a lot in
common
not culturally but geopolitically our
interests align to a significant extent
India wants peace in the Middle East
India wants excellent relations with all
the nations in the Middle East
especially those that matter Israel
certainly matters so I think India and
Israel have an excellent relationship uh
the relationship has really taken off
after the uh Advent of Mr Modi as a
prime minister of India and Mr Modi has
shares an excellent relationship with
with prime minister Netanyahu of Israel
the Israeli political system is very uh
unstable governments come and fall you
have coalitions and right now there is
you know this weird not weird but
expected
uh
activity happening in Israel Mr
Netanyahu was trying to reform the
judicial system and make it more Pro
people and more in the control of the
people and as expected you know there
was almost like a like a color
Revolution situation that happened
overnight out of thin air
and what I I don't I don't think it's
very hard to see where it came from who
was who was trying to engineer that
so I think we should support Mr
Netanyahu India India and Israel if we
work together there's a lot we can
achieve together uh so the relations
between India and Israel overall are are
excellent and even if some other prime
minister comes into the picture in in
Israel the relations will still remain
excellent because it's a logic of
strategy India and Israel have a lot
um the natural the national interests
converge and align to a significant
interests uh it was too significant
extent culturally we are very different
India and Israel have almost nothing in
common when it comes to culture but that
doesn't matter
it's the it's the alignment and
convergence of interests geopolitically
that really matters in the in the in the
in the context of the relationship
between the two Nations
okay
jitendra says my fur my top five world
war movies my top five world war movies
um I can think of a movie made in the
1960s or something called the longest
day that was a good movie lots of uh
prominent actors from the time I could
think of Saving Private Ryan which was a
very graphic portrayal of the of the
Normandy invasion the D-Day beaches of
Normandy it's five starts with you it
starts by putting you in media race in
middle of the action the first scene
itself you know landing on the beaches
so um Saving Private Ryan was good
I've seen so many Escape to Victory or
whatever it's about uh uh Escape to
Victory escape to freedom I forget the
name it was once again uh an ensemble
caste uh what else I've seen so many of
these movies second world war movies I
cannot even remember all of them
First World War I I I saw a Soviet movie
A harrowing Soviet movie I think it was
from the Second World War I forget the
name of the movie
it was a movie from the 1980s it was
like really harrowing you never want to
see War if you see that movie
um
what else what else
yeah I can't remember the names I
typically am very bad with remembering
names and all that uh but yeah all quiet
along the western front is a new movie
that's come out I hear it's good uh I
saw Dunkirk which I didn't quite like
because it kind of tried to whitewash
the the contribution of Indians but
stylistically Etc it was a good movie
gripping movie
um
and and I'm sure there are more yeah so
anyway good question good question
interesting question I I actually am a
big fan of movies I like watching movies
and these days we don't have any good
movies yeah new movies
uh um
okay what else
ubendran says how would the world's
countries react if we suddenly change
our education system and teach our
children Real History the way it should
be taught well I would say most of the
world would be indifferent or they would
welcome it I am talking about the global
South will anybody in Africa have any
issue with that nobody in Africa will
have an issue with that will anybody in
eastern Asia have an issue with that the
Chinese will actually say good
Southeast Asian countries like Vietnam
Laos Cambodia Indonesia and so on they
will also welcome it the couriers will
commit the Japanese will welcome it the
Russians will welcome it
the nations in South America will also
say good who cares
so which nations will have an issue with
this
it's the Nations that are part of the
anglosphere or under the hegemony of the
anglosphere I'm talking about the EU
Nations the NATO Nations and the US and
the five I five eyes Alliance they will
have an issue with this
and they are maybe five or ten percent
of the world's population so
overwhelmingly the world won't care or
will be positively incline will have a
positive reaction it is these little
this little bunch of Nations which are
which have which essentially have all
the power in the world they will have an
issue with this they want India to
remain mentally colonized
they want Indians to grow up
feeling their culture is is inferior to
the Western culture
they want Indians to feel to grow up
feeling ashamed of their culture in
their heritage
so India is still colonized because of
the education system so if we change the
education system it is the
English-speaking countries and their
minions who will have an issue with this
nobody else and it will be their agents
within India who will protest
so we have the entire education system
is is essentially you know especially
when it comes to the humanities it's
filled with these individuals the
so-called eminent professors Etc who
have been carrying The White Man's
Burden
and there's a term for that and some
people allege it's racist I can't be
racist against my own people
so these people are brown coolies
the ones who are carrying The White
Man's Burden and furthering the white
man's agenda
I have nothing against the white metal
so the Russians are also white I have
nothing against them it's uh
it's not really the White Man's Burden
it's the Anglo-Saxon Man's Burden that
they are carrying
uh so yeah that's what I think most of
the world will be either indifferent or
will have a positive reaction to this
it's only the the colonialists who are
still actively colonizing the world who
will
uh protest and react negatively
okay Aditya says recently SpaceX
conducted a launch of a mega rocket
Starship but it failed because of engine
failure is Israel also working on such
Mega projects
um
so it was not really a failure the the
Starship is the biggest uh and most
powerful rocket the space that SpaceX
has ever built and it's the most
powerful rocket the the world has ever
seen it's more powerful than uh the
space launch system SLS of of NASA
uh and it's also more powerful than the
Saturn V rocket that Werner Von Brown
Built For The Americans
uh in the 960s which took the first
people to the Moon Neil Armstrong was
already in and all that
so this Starship rocket see when you are
testing a rocket there are multiple
phases of tests
the only objective of this test was to
see whether this rocket the entire
assembled rocket fully assembled rocket
can lift off and clear the launching pad
if it did that it was a success that's
the only thing
that's what Elon Musk very clearly said
weeks before the launch that we will
consider this a success if it takes off
and clears the launching pad it went
about 13 kilometers into the air so it
was a proper
success it was not a failure of course
it it they eventually uh
blew it up it was a
they decided to expose to to blow it up
so that it doesn't end up somewhere it
should not be so they they remotely
detonated the rocket it's called a rapid
unscheduled disassembly
which is a rather humorous term for uh
an intentional explore you know
destruction of rocket
so when when it was uh when it was going
up into the air
while it was climbing you could see it
has I think it had 33 Raptor engines out
of which not all 33 were were ignited
some of them had gone off so yeah that
was something that they'll need to work
on so the system can clearly take off on
it or take take off properly and go and
launch itself into the air it it flew 13
kilometers into the air even without
even after some of the rocket engines
failed so overall it was a great great
success and that's how you
create that's how you test out a new
system there are multiple tests your
first test will not succeed entirely
even if your first test fails completely
it gives you a huge amount of data which
tells you what you need to improve
so in India we have so such small
budgets that we hope that every test we
can only test the rocket once and every
test has to be a success full success
that's not how it's done ideally ideally
you have the budget to conduct multiple
rapid tests so you launch the system
today it succeeds let's sit to a certain
extent and the other part fails and
whatever fails you get the data back
from the sensors and all that then you
understand what went wrong you implement
the changes and within a month or two
you test it again then let's say
something some more things work but
something still fail so keep on testing
you have to keep testing rapidly not
once in 10 years
not once in five years not once a year
you test 10 or 20 times in a year that's
how you perfect a system very rapidly
for that you need budget a big budget
so I don't think it's a failure I think
it's a success
it's a success because they were able to
validate certain Technologies the ones
they really wanted to validate they are
the ones they will perfect later on so
the next launch is coming up within two
months and that launch will most likely
be more successful than this one maybe
it should attain orbit maybe they will
not have to blow it up
or even if they have to blow it up they
will be most likely able to go Way
Beyond the 13 kilometers altitude that
this rocket was able to achieve so yeah
that's how it's done
now is ISRO working on such Mega
projects I think ISRO is working on a
Next Generation rocket system
uh which would be modular in in
its uh
design
but I'm not sure what the status is
um
the the most powerful rocket that ISRO
has is the gsra Mark III or the SLS I
don't know what they call it these days
the the most powerful gslv they have
renamed it to something else these days
uh it's it's a it's the most powerful
rocket that India has but in in
comparison with the other rockets that
the world has for instance the Ariane
system the Chinese Long March system the
Rockets the Russians soyuz uh and other
rockets in the American Rockets uh you
when you compare the GS GSL Mach 3 with
the other Rockets you'll find that it's
a it's a medium launch vehicle a light
to medium launch vehicle it's not a
heavy launch vehicle
in India ISRO has the technology and the
understanding
and the ability and the talent to build
a rocket that's at least 10 times more
powerful for that it will need the
approval from the government and the
funding to do this
and once again they'll be expected to
have success on the first try itself
because the funding will be so limited
that's the problem with the Indian Space
Program it's it's a lack of funding and
a lack of I don't know
uh I don't know maybe the Indian
leadership doesn't see the space as
something as a that's worthy of being
prioritized right now perhaps they're
right I don't know obviously they know
things much better than me they know
things about the world that I am not
able to see they have information and
data and insights that we common people
do not have obviously so maybe they are
right from from in what they're doing
but
the thing is if we if we increase the
budget of Israel let's say 10 times it's
not a huge amount let's say you increase
it 10 times ideally then imagine what it
should be able to do within two to three
years it will have a rocket that's
easily 10 times more powerful than the
GS will be Mark III
so I don't know if Israel is working on
such projects we I mean I do know that
uh
such a more powerful rocket is being
planned I don't know what the status is
what what is it in the conceptual stage
is it in the fabrication stage are we
anywhere closing close to testing it I
have no idea because no such information
has been released uh in the future let
me see if I can talk to somebody from
ISRO and and find out what's actually
happening but right now we don't know
all right
says is it true that ancient India China
and Persia were the three super
civilizations and superpowers of Ancient
Asia
uh it depends on which time frame you're
looking at we see when we are taking a
photograph it we have different lenses
we have a camera body which costs x
amount of money and then we have an
assortment of lenses so if you want to
take a picture at a very you know of us
very small let's say you want to
photograph in ant you take a certain
lens certain lenses won't work for that
it depends on the focal length
let's say if you want a wide angle View
then you will have to need use a you
know a certain kind of focal length and
all that and if you want to do to look
at something very far away you need to
do to use a different kind of length a
different kind of lens so there are
there's a wide variety of lenses for
different purposes there are telephoto
lenses that are very very shallow depth
of field lenses and so on
similarly when you are studying the
history of a Nation or a civilization it
all you will the the kind of image you
get
the image you get the understanding you
get depends on the lens that you use
what do I mean by lens
the time frame are you looking at a
nation from a hundred year window
only the past 100 years then you will
get a certain perspective as children we
see India as what it is today and that's
why we tend to blame our own people for
for whatever India whatever is wrong
with India if you take a thousand year
lens then you will see what was done to
India if you look at if you read the
right sources from the right sources
then you will see a different
perspective if you if you take a 2000
year lens and you examine the history of
the past 2000 years it gives you a whole
different perspective let's say you take
a 5000 year lens then it gives you a
whole different context so the question
is when we when it comes to India China
Persia what lens are we gonna use
ideally you want the longest lens
possible
for China you need a lens that is 3000
years old you need a time frame of 3000
years so you need a reasonably long lens
for that 3000 years or maybe three and a
half thousand years when it comes to
Persia once again
three or three and a half thousand years
I mean the oldest Dynasty that we know
of the haksha Manish Dynasty the cabinet
Dynasty is about it it's its origin is
about around
around 1000 BC or slightly after that
maybe 900 BC or so
or 800 BC somewhere around in in that
time period That's when haksha Manish
the progenitor the the founder of the
Dynasty is said to have lived in raid
but the history of the people of Persia
is older
the people of Persia
are essentially migrants from India
right and before zorothism we all know
what the culture and religion of Persia
was it was nothing but their form of
Vedic Hinduism or post Vedic Hinduism
um
so Persia is a daughter civilization of
India so if we take a 3000 year lens of
world history then you had three great
civilizations India China Persia and
China was confined to the east it is not
today is China
see let's let's take a look at the map
right it's important to understand this
when it comes to China
the geographical extent of China was was
Eastern China it was not Tibet it was
not xinjiang East Turkestan it was not
inner Mongolia it was not Yunnan it was
not Manchuria it was only the eastern
part of China the Beijing Shanghai
region maybe chonking
you know the the heavy dense Network
that is here roads that is
that too is much larger than ancient
China
so ancient China was the Han region was
in the East so it was nowhere close to
the size of the Indian subcontinent
and it was most likely perhaps smaller
than present-day Iran that was ancient
China so it was not a super civilization
it was a civilization a respectable
civilization
and they had conquestion Wars most of
the great Wars that the Chinese fought
were amongst each other among themselves
whenever a foreigner actually invaded
China and and brought War to Chinese
territory the Chinese typically lost
that's a different story so if we take a
3000 year lens you had three
civilizations India China and Persia
Persia was coming into its full might in
glory India was the oldest civilization
at least 10 000 years old and India
spanned the entire Indian subcontinent
including Gandhara which is present-day
Afghanistan and there are indianized
kingdoms all across Central Asia
including present-day Tibet in
present-day so-called xinjiang of China
so much of Central Asia was indianized
at the time Iran itself was an
indianized civilization which later
acquired its own characteristics via
zoroastrinism
um so when it comes to Super
civilizations I think
when it comes to from from the from the
perspective of antiquity as well as from
the perspective of geographical extent
India was a super civilization Persia
was not that large geographically
neither was China
uh in India in Persia were very closely
uh related culturally ethnically
genetically linguistically also and if
you look at the history of Persia
of uh before the the Arabic Islamic
invasion of Persia the entire 1500 or so
year history of Persia they always waged
war northwards or westwards they never
ever
even once in recorded history tried to
fight India or invade India that tells
you a story of the relationship between
India brochure
so there were three great civilizations
yes but the super civilization whether
you agree or not was India and if we go
back with a even longer lens 5000 year
lens there wasn't any China there wasn't
any Persia it was just India you go back
10 000 years we still had India so yeah
interesting
okay
says Hindu Hindu temples older than the
Chula period are found in Cambodia yes
when did Hindus reach these lands first
once again we go back to the map
there are temples all across all across
southeast Asia all all the way in
Indonesia across uh southeast Asia Laos
Cambodia Vietnam Thailand Myanmar and
you have Indian influence all the way
into Korea and Japan
so it is true 100 sure true that there
are Hindu temples
that are found in Cambodia that that
predate the Chola invasion of Southeast
Asia the Chola conquest of Southeast
Asia happened a thousand years before
today
it was all the way up to the Philippines
but this region was indianized way
before the Chulas ever appeared here
so how was this how did that happen
so you had something called The funan
Kingdom in Vietnam that dates back to at
least I think roughly two thousand years
before today
the founder of the funan kingdom was a
local Queen who married an Indian
Merchant
so the so the founders of the fulan
Kingdom were were an Indian king who was
married to a local uh uh lady from from
this region
and uh so the first Indian influence
in Southeast Asia
it dates back to I would say at least
3000 years before today and it all came
from Kalinga
so we have this very ancient tradition
in our odisha which was then called
Kalinga of trading with suvarna bhumi
and Beyond so nabumi is Thailand and
Beyond is southeast Asia Vietnam
Cambodia Laos
um Philippines and Indonesia so it is
initially the the people of Kalinga who
established you know very strong trade
and cultural relations with the lands of
Eastern Asia especially Southeast Asia
and it is they who brought in Indian
culture first
so you find a ancient temples in
Southeast Asia all across southeast Asia
whether it's Myanmar or Thailand or
Cambodia or Vietnam or Laos or anywhere
else these temples date back to 2000 or
even more years before today
and Nations have even gone to war over
temples there is something called the
Priya vihar Temple which lies the the
the border of Thailand and Cambodia let
me let me show that the Priya vihar
Temple
let me Google that
and put that on the screen
okay where is it yeah here we are the
Priya vihar Temple this is a temple
that's on the exact border of Thailand
and Cambodia and in the early 2000s the
two Nations almost went to war over this
Temple both these nations
claimed this this sacred Temple it's in
Ruins it's very ancient it's I don't
know how old it is close to 2000 years
old I'm sure maybe more than that it's
in Ruins it's a Hindu Shiva Temple
and the two Nations went to war over a
ruined Temple nearly went to war they
had to go to the U.N I think to resolve
the dispute
it was a very serious dispute
Temple and there was a if you if you
look at the Wikipedia article it will
show that there was this
ownership dispute the two Nations nearly
went to war the international court of
justice was brought in and they had they
gave a judgment
they they declared the temple belonged
to Cambodia and Thailand had to withdraw
all the troops
so so that's how these nations and the
in the people of Southeast Asia even
today value
what is now their culture but it which
which came from India they value Indian
culture more than we evaluate ourselves
can you believe it
we in India are completely deracinated
we are all non-practicing whatever
Hindus Buddhists whatever most of us
most of us have no connection anymore
with our culture and when it comes to
Nations like like Thailand and Cambodia
they nearly went to war over an ancient
2000 years roughly two thousand year old
ruin Temple
Hindu temple both these nations are
classified as Buddhist countries
right
you ask any historian you ask any
sociologist you ask anybody they will
say Thailand is a is about this country
and Cambodia is a Buddhist country
and this Temple was a Hindu temple there
is no Buddhist element in this Temple
it's ruin it's ruined and still these
donations almost went to war that was
firing there are troops on both sides it
was almost a warlike situation
in these clashes
so yeah so the hint so Hinduism or
Indian culture whatever you want to call
it reach these lands at least 3000 years
before today through the great traders
of Kalinga which is which is this
tradition is still celebrated in in
odisha uh the Bali yatra tradition the
boitabandana and much more and we have
totally forgotten this your rubila
thapas and other historians will not
teach you about this they don't want you
to know about this glorious great
tradition that that we had that the
great land of Kalinga had
okay
Jesus says is the story of civilization
series by Will Duran still relevant
today I think it's still very relevant
today obviously it was written almost a
century ago but the information that it
contains is still very
true much of it most of it I would say
is very true it's very detailed it's
very accurate it's very interesting I
read it as a kid
I read it as a kid I don't know how old
I was 10 years old 12 years old I was
engrossed with these big thick books it
was more interesting than any novel you
read so these are wonderful books they
are obviously there is obviously much
more information that we have today
much more many more discoveries have
been made much more much better
understanding is available of these
civilizations in periods of history that
they wrote about and yet it's still very
relevant I would say if you are really
seriously under interested in learning
history world history especially it's an
invaluable resource the story of
Civilization by Will and Ariel Durant
okay
what's your view regarding India and Sri
Lanka I like India I like Sri Lanka
I would say I love India and I also love
Sri Lanka you know uh when it comes to
the relationship between India and Sri
Lanka I think India and Sri Lanka
have a very good relationship there have
been Rocky periods in the past because
in the past India's leaders did not
prioritize India's national interest and
the subcontinents or shared interests
and they did the stupid things
overall I I see Sri Lanka the people of
Sri Lanka is the same as the people of
India yes of course we respect the fact
that Sri Lanka is a separate nation
state and we respect that very much but
I think the relationship between Indian
Sri Lanka can take the form that the
relationship between India and Nepal as
we I don't see why we need to have
passports and visas all that why don't
we just have open borders we can have
we can have much more integration of the
two Nations you know I think something
like that is actually afoot the two
governments especially the Sri Lankan
government has proposed something and
that's something that's been being
worked on so the same energy grid uh
significant interconnected connectedness
in the education systems the the
governance systems of free flow of
people no visa requirements all that
and uh why can't the people of Sri Lanka
be given the right to come and live in
India and work in India the same way the
people of Nepal are given the same right
we are the same people we look the same
we sound the same you know so it's it's
a it's an accident of history that we
are two Nations separate Nations and
that's fine we we have no desire to
reintegrate Sri Lanka into India or
anything we can we can have a United
States of extended India in the future
right in which we remain separate
separate nation states but uh we are way
more integrated than other nations would
be so I think there is and Sri Lanka is
a wonderful place great great uh people
great local
beautiful manifestation of culture
localized culture there uh beautiful
terrain beautiful geography uh great
beaches I think there's a tremendous
potential for tourism in Sri Lanka from
the perspective of Adventure tourism and
and the nature natural environment that
you have and the culture also
um so I think the future is really uh
going to be good for the relationship
between India and Sri Lanka and I would
like to see much better and much Freer
people to people uh exchanges and
movements and interconnectivity so I
think I think that's going to happen in
the next let's say a decade or so
all right uh let's take some more
questions
um
yeah this is a question I get all the
time can I explain about ashoka's nine
men the secret society well uh I don't
know if the society exists or not it is
claimed it is uh some books some
historians some writers have written
about this that the emperor Ashoka maybe
something somebody before him also
created a sister a secret society of
nine great
intellectuals and Scholars who would
preserve India's wisdom and knowledge
over the Millennia
people with
specialized knowledge and and you know
that sort of thing so I don't know if
it's true or not if it's a secret
society it's going to be secret right so
well
that's the thing I mean I get this
question all the time I don't know I
have no idea uh you will not see any any
evidence of this anywhere I mean if
there are nine secret nine men today who
are part of the society continuation of
that obviously if this exists they will
not reveal themselves yeah I'm part of
the society no you don't do that you
keep it quiet so the answer is we don't
talk about it if it exists
um
Ari says can you talk can you speak
about the sokotra island given its
location strategic location can end will
any future or current superpower take
control of it for example Bharat okay
good question excellent question let's
find sokotra
it's not really far from India actually
you know let's find it on the map it
belongs to even by the way Yemen it is a
part of the nation state of Yemen so we
know where India is we know where the
Sea of saurashtra is so-called Arabian
Sea temporarily
so you go there you go eastwards towards
our neighboring Nations Oman and Yemen
and Somalia and you find this little
island here it's not so little it's
actually quite big
this is the island of sokotra once again
zoom out zoom out and you see where it
is in relation to India it is off the
west coast of India very close to the
Gulf of Arden
off the coast of Somalia and Yemen
now how large is it it's a significantly
large island tip to tip east to west it
is about uh 130 kilometers and north to
south at the largest extent it's about
uh 43 kilometers it's a large island
it has a
it has clearly it has settlements in
cities and towns looks like
yeah it has it has some human activity
uh so that is sokotra as you can see
it's it's in a very strategic location
it's at the gulf at the mouth of the
Gulf of Arden
uh it is at the Horn of Africa so you
can control it can oversee all shipping
and all trade activity coming in from
the Suez Canal region if you if you
don't know where so where is it is over
here
alsoise
also ice oh yeah there's a canal that
that slices through uh the Sinai region
and Egypt so that's where all the
shipping comes in from through the Red
Sea into the Gulf of Aden and if you are
sitting in sokotra if you have a naval
presence there or Air Force presence
there you can control the entire
shipping and trade
that flows between Eastern Asia and the
Western world
um
very strategic location and it currently
belongs to emn I don't think any other
nation has a military presence over
there in the future if Other Nations
become powerful there will certainly be
tempted tempted the Temptation will
exist to take control of sakotra for
sure because if you have
let's say a bunch of fighter planes
there you can really take control of the
entire
region if you have a navel present there
a bunch of Destroyers
maybe a few submarines stationed there
aha good fun so yes that's sokotra
Island historically there has been an
Indian presence there way before any
Arabic presence I'll not go into the
history but yeah and if you see the
people of Yemen most of them look like
Indians so there's a whole history there
whole story whole story there which will
not we will not open that box right now
but yes in the future if new superpowers
exist or emerge they will certainly be
tempted to take over sakotra
uh um
ritesh Jas sir like how South Indian
kingdoms raided Sri Lanka many times
like that was there any Empire that did
the opposite and invaded India
well when it comes to Lanka the the
original inhabitants see we have the
ramayan story The the events of the
ramayana which happened like several
thousand years ago and we had a king
there ravan
and uh there was a population in Sri
Lanka people who lived there and the
places still exist the the
places mentioned in the ramayan still
exist in Sri Lanka so
so you had people there and culturally
nothing anything ethnically they were
clearly the same as Indians later on we
had the Advent of the sinhalese people
um with the Advent of Prince Vijay
into Sri Lanka who most likely came from
odisha most likely from Kalinga
so what I'm trying to say is that there
is no difference ethnically culturally
genetically
even linguistically real difference
between the people of Sri Lanka and the
people of India later on the Tamil
people also were settled there by the
British and even before the British I'm
sure
there's no real difference right so um
so Sri Lanka has historically today it's
a separate nation state historically it
was part of various kingdoms
you had Kingdoms in Sri Lanka as well
and there was constant inter marriage
between the Kings between the royal
families in Lanka in Sri Lanka and the
royal families in let's say the Tamil
parts of India in other parts of India
so you will you would have had raids
from in conquests back and forth for
sure similarly was there any Empire that
the opposite in India I mean um
please look at the past 1000 Years or
1200 years of Indian history
it's it's what I call the Millennium of
humiliation humiliation
India was repeatedly invaded
by first the Arabs then the Turks
and over a period of five centuries they
were able to make inroads into India and
they conquered India eventually
and they established the turko Mughal
Empire before that delhi's alternative
had other things as well after the the
destruction after the fall downfall of
the turkic empire in India the so called
Mughal Empire
the marathas defeated them then you had
the European
rule over India because they were
rapidly able to defeat the maratha
Empire and then there was British rule
in India and that's why we speak English
today so that's what happened right I
mean
that's the past 1000 years of Indian
history in the past you had invasions
before that
attempted invasions of India the Huns
tried to invade India
they were repelled multiple times by the
Gupta Emperors especially uh skanda
Gupta the great skanda Gupta eventually
they were able to make inroads into
India but they assimilated harmoniously
into the Indian population they never
tried to bring in a foreign religion or
cultural language into India
um before the Huns you had this kittians
and the kushans who also were able to
invade Northern Western India and
Conquer parts of India and they also
harmoniously assimilated into India
whether ever without ever trying to
impose a foreign language or culture or
religion into India so you had multiple
see India is such a large place you have
these back and forth migrations in
attempted invasions all that Alexander
tried to do that it cost him his life
yeah
so it's a it's a long story you had so
many such instances when such things
happened
Nippon says what really happened with
Chandra and too we suddenly lost the
connection and the Rover was not
deployed it went upside down and it
crashed it essentially the last moment
so was there some kind of geopolitical
Reason well what we know is this I I was
up all night I was on times now I was
covering it live I was I was part of the
panel on times now that was covering the
live chandrayaan
Landing attempt
so the chandrayaan uh Orbiter was
deployed around the Moon it was it was
doing perfectly well and then it it uh
released the the Vikram Lander I think
it was called and it would it rapidly uh
reduced its altitude and eventually it
was to autonomously land do a soft
landing on the surface of the Moon
it had its own AI system its own
computer because the this distance from
the Earth to the Moon is not trivial if
you send a light signal to the Moon it
takes about close to half a second to
reach there and if you were to get a
signal back from the Moon it will take
another half a second so that's a delay
of one second and when you're remotely
controlling
a Lander which is flying in the air and
you wanted to land softly and gently you
can't have a delay of one second roughly
one second or slightly more than one
second that's why this Rover was given
uh in intelligence of its own in an
autonomous Landing system of its own and
we were getting uh
a link a relay back to Earth of what was
happening and that's how we knew what
what was it was a condition of the Rover
so it was going down towards the towards
the lunar soil surface it had multiple
thrusters and all that and what we find
is that the essentially the almost the
last minute the Rover the Lander flips
upside down
and then it it had an uncontrolled
descent and crashed onto the sofa Moon
and eventually we were able to a few
months later see the photographs of the
crashed Lander and Rover it was a dual
system it's a Lander which contained a
Rover inside Vikram Lander Vikram row or
whatever it was called
whatever the two components were
so um the question is was there a
geopolitical reason
look it's possible that if your
Communications are not entirely secure
or not secure enough that somebody may
be able to hack into your system and
take control
of your Lander or maybe give it the
wrong commands
or maybe disrupt the communication and
do something so it was alleged that some
some
foreign power may possibly perhaps
have done such a thing
and at the same time that this thing was
happening the The Landing attempt there
was also a big security breach a hack
into uh an Indian nuclear
uh
Nuclear Station
which uh also was quite significant at
the time these things were hushed up
obviously for good reason because we
don't want to talk about this too much
uh but yeah two things happened more or
less at the same time
a breach a security breach
cyber security breach of an Indian
nuclear system and also the crash of the
Vikram of the chandrayaan to Lander and
Rover
so there was speculation at the time
that there may have been
a foreign hand in this and the
possibility the probability of there
being a foreign hand in this is not zero
it definitely exists okay
so who was it what who was behind this
was it indeed the case well I think
someday the story will come out
all right
okay
well if it is if it is still around it's
Kuwait 23. I think the virus is gonna
remain there
it's gonna become like an endemic kind
of virus it's already kind of an endemic
virus the media still tries to create
this this you know this this uh this
hype that cases are rising again enough
nobody cares anymore okay it's one of
the weakest and mildest viruses that to
ever exist of course it killed people
that's what viruses do they weed out
the unfit
people in society that is the harsh
reality of life I'm not saying viruses
are good but viruses exist you you deal
with it so when it comes to
virulence in mortality the covid-19
virus was one of the weakest viruses of
all time nothing like the mortality rate
of the Spanish Flu for instance which
was actually a Chinese flow
um and various other pandemics that we
have experienced this was one of the
mildest pandemics of course it killed
millions of people because that's what
happens even the weakest microorganism
even the weakest pathogen will take out
some members of your population a small
sub percentage 0.1 percent or whatever
that's that's bound to happen
but overall it's it's
overall most people gain natural
immunity from it most people
uh people with pre-existing uh
conditions
people with diabetes for instance people
who smoke a lot or even smoke people
with high blood pressure people with
cancer people with these pre-existing
conditions they were prone
to you know getting into trouble with
coordinated for most people there was no
such issue
so India was the nation that was the
most proactive India made the best
vaccine India inoculated and vaccinated
its population in an extremely rapid and
efficient manner and for us in India we
need to put this behind us okay
everybody is vaccinated
and we have dealt with the entire
situation now the media will will keep
on trying to create a new hype about
kovid9 completely ignore that everybody
is vaccinated why do we need more hype
now
what they're trying to do is they're
trying to make make this set the stage
for maybe introducing new vaccine
booster doses or whatever or start or
you know people I know well you know
take names but there were certain Indian
celebrities writers Etc who were trying
to Shell
for modern
and for Pfizer for Pfizer as a special
especially to bring in the Pfizer
vaccine to India and now it's so clear
that the Pfizer vaccine has killed more
people than it is saved that's an
atrociously bad vaccine and the Americas
are still pushing pushing for booster
doses in the U.S
so so the my perspective was very clear
the Indian vaccine is the best vaccines
it's performed the best the worst
vaccine has been the Chinese vaccine
because it has not saved anybody it has
been the most poorly performing the most
inefficient vaccine and the most
dangerous vaccine has been the Pfizer
vaccine
we in India are perfectly safe everybody
is vaccinated so we need to put covid-19
behind us enough and if the media still
tries to create a hype ignore them and
if they still keep on doing it
unsubscribe from them and block them
that's what I would suggest
okay maybe one or two questions more
something are not taken before
Shaheen says historically this
justinians plague in the Byzantine
Empire and Sicilian Empire lasted nearly
a century with many outbreaks happening
every decade the Justinian Justinian's
plague and later the Black Death Etc
these were horrific events uh yeah it
totally ravaged the Byzantine Empire and
the neighboring sasanian Empire and then
you in the in the with Sanji 13th or
14th century you have the black black
death in in Europe
which came later which I think killed a
quarter or or a third or maybe a half of
Europe's entire population
disaster horrific disasters
so these these were the real dangers
that we have overcome our ancestors in
India none of these things came none of
these horrible plague and other
pandemics ever made their way into India
for some reason
why well ask yourselves why they
completely bypass India and they went
all across the other other parts of the
world they ravaged China they ravaged to
Central Asia and their ravaged Europe
and also to some extent Persia to some
extent not as much as Europe
all right I think we are done for today
we have as always huge huge amounts of
questions
um
yeah I think I think I'm gonna stop oh
yeah it's two hours ten minutes
otherwise we can do this all night also
all day also but yeah let's let's send
it over here so everybody thank you very
much for the questions thank you for
your participation thank you for
for your viewership and I will see you
very soon in the next live stream until
then take care thank you very much
and keep raising your standards thank
you bye